Estimated expected value right and likewise
at the end to recommend a specific arm I also
use the estimated expected value right there
is a whole other class of algorithms that
directly work with the directly work with
the representation of the policy right so
what do I mean by a policy here, I told you
what a policy was in the very first class
right what is the policy, I said its a mapping
from States to actions or states to action
probabilities right in this case we really
have no states right so far we have not considered
any states.
So what would a policy be in this case sorry
yeah it could be just one arm or it could
be some kind of a probability distribution
over the arms right it could be one arm or
some probability distribution over the arms
so I am going to denote this by right, so
which is the probability of pulling arm a
right and my goal is to keep changing this
policy over time, such that eventually I will
be recommending with probability one to pull
the best arm right.
So this policy is going to keep changing over
time so I am going to denote this by hmm..so
the policy is going to keep changing over
time and denote this by pi t right, so now
what a learning algorithm has to do in such
a case is it has to give me a way of changing
this pi t with time right, so one way of thinking
about things like epsilon greedy right or
soft max is that they define this pi t in
an indirect fashion right if you remember
I wrote it down also right.
I wrote I wrote down what pi t would be for
epsilon greedy and soft max I started off
by writing it for soft max then i came back
and wrote it down for epsilon greedy right
people remember that I said what will be the
probability of picking I don't know if I used
the pi notation did I use the pi notation
? yes, I use P the probability of picking
action right I didn't because I didn't introduce
the pi notation I did not think I used it
but essentially the probability of picking
an action I would have written probability
at equal to a right, that is exactly what
pi t of a is right.
So this is, it is a probability that at equal
to a to this is additional notation we will
be using the notation pi throughout right,
so later we will use will condition this on
this states also that will essentially be
the probability that at equal to a given st
equal to s right, here since there's only
one state we do not have to do that great,
so some of the earliest known approaches for
solving bandits use this kind of a direct
policy search right.
So some kind of a policy search approach right
so in that what we do is, so let us let us
keep it simple I will talk about a two action
case right and then we can talk about other
things right so a very very simplified situation
which is called the
binary bandit where there are only two outcomes
either you get a 0 or you get a 1 right, so
1 is a good outcome 0 is a bad outcome this
just makes me I am just going to give you
like the historic perspective here okay.
So in fact it is so historic that in edition
2 they got rid of all of this discussion in
the book, right so if you want to know more
about the kind of things I am talking about
right now you will have to go back and read
edition one of the RL book, so let us say
I will talk about binary bandits, so Rt can
be either 0 or 1 okay, and let us say I have
a two armed bandit case here so I have only
arm 1 or arm 2 just to make my thing easy.
So if right at some time t, Rt equal to 1
right, then what I will do is I will make,
pi t plus 1 of at essentially the action I
took at time t right, a t is the action I
took at time T and the reward I got was 1
so what should I do, hmm, should increase
all right so how will I do that right, so
if alpha is small enough ok, so the best action
will eventually converge to a probability
of 1 if alpha is very large I will start oscillating
this will this might not be probabilities
all those problems are there right.
And what about the other case if this is this
if I am doing this, the action some other
action a prime
what should I do for that right, I mean ideally
it should be plus alpha times 0 minus pi so
this will work if it is two actions if its
multiple actions what happens, it will not
be a probability distribution I will have
to make sure that everything stays a probability
distribution, right if there are multiple
actions instead of taking alpha from everybody,
then I should take away alpha by n minus 1
from the other actions okay.
So that when I sum up everything after that
also it will still be 1, starting off with
assumption that pi t sums to 1, so I need
to make sure pi t plus 1 also sums to 1, so
I will have to adjust these numbers accordingly
okay, so I am pretty sure all of you can do
the correct adjustment, so this is essentially
one update rule one sec what happens any ideas
hmm..sorry..I got 0, the reward was 0, this
1 has nothing to do with the reward okay.
In fact this 1 here has nothing to do with
the reward the 1 here it has to do with the
fact that if the probability I would like
this probability to be 1 you remember the
form of the rule I told you right, current
value target minus the current value, so the
error right so current value plus alpha times
error so that is the thing it's the same way
here the probability I want is 0 okay, so
it is the current value plus alpha times 0
minus pi, so I simplified that I wrote it
as 1 minus alpha right.
So I'm always writing it in the same stochastic
averaging form right, so the 1 is the target
I want this is not the reward right, suppose
i got a reward of zero what do I do, you flip
it around right it turns out that well that
is one valid option there are many options
that you can have right, so just flip this
around right, I reduce the probability of
the action at took at time t, I increase the
probability of the action I took I didn't
take at time t right.
So why do I have to do this just to make sure
it is a probability distribution right when
I reduce this probability this will automatically
have to go up, it is not like I am rewarding
the action I didn't take right, but the fact
we have this constraint of the probabilities
have to sum to 1 we will automatically reward
the other action, okay so but notice i wrote
alpha and beta, so depending on the relationship
between alpha and beta.
So you have different kinds of algorithms
right so if alpha equal to beta, so we have
something called, something called linear
reward penalty LRP algorithm okay, so it's
this these things have been around for many
many many decades ok, so the LRP algorithm
is linear because the relationships there
is all linear so you can see there are no
higher order terms in the updates that you
write, so you have.. you do something you
change the parameters on a reward and you
also change the parameters when you get a
penalty right.
So the reward is plus 1, penalty is 0 and
you are changing them by equal amounts right,
that is when alpha equal to beta, so when
alpha is much greater than beta right, remember
these are relative terms okay, when I say
alpha much greater than beta still alpha is
very small and I expect alpha to be like 10
power minus 3 or 10 power minus 2 or something
like that right even though I write alpha
is far far greater than beta that means beta
should be 10 power minus 5 or 10 power minus
7 something much smaller right this is called
L R epsilon P.
So I do something when I get a reward right
I do a much much smaller change when I get
a penalty ok, any idea what the I stands for
yeah, it stands for inaction but yeah you
get the idea right so when rewards comes I
do something when the penalty side of it happens
I do nothing, in action I just leave the probabilities
as it is okay and it turns out that there
is very very small change right the algorithm
itself is the same all I am doing is changing
these things around and it turns out the convergence
behaviors of these three algorithms are very
different right and depending on how how rewarding
your arms are right.
So for example my best arm let us say has
a probability of, say a binary bandit right
0 or 1, let us say my best arm has a probability
of say 0.9 of coming up as 1, right and the
other arm has say a probability of 0.6 of
coming up as 1, then LRP will work well right,
but suppose my best arm has probability of
0.3 of coming up as 1 right and my bad arm
my worst arm has a probability of 0.2 of coming
up as 1 or 0.25 of coming up as 1, LRP is
going to have a hard time in fact it turns
out that in such cases LRI works better because
whenever a small reward comes also you whenever
the reward comes right you keep hiking the
probability right, because the probability
of getting the reward is so small right.
So if I am doing something on the penalty
side I always almost always be depressing
my probabilities I will just keep decreasing
the probabilities and increasing the other
probability so there will be a lot of oscillations
right, so in cases where rewards are scarce
to come by its best to ignore the penalties
right so there are many many things like this
so yeah, so there is still a very vibrant
community that works with this kind of learning
automaton ideas and this is the most basic
most fundamental of these things I told you
about this variable structure stochastic automata
right, I asked you about finite state machines
and you all of you said you know finite state
machines right and I told you then there is
this variable structure finite state machines
as people use for solving.
So these are kind of the culmination of the
variable structure finite state machines right
so you can go down and write it more explicitly
as to how it turns out to be automata right,
but this is more of a compact way of representing
those variable structure finite automata so
I am not going to get into too much detail
even though there is a vibrant community that
does this, right and so this is just to tell
you that this history of using this policy
representations directly right goes back several
decades in fact the earliest such learning
automaton method was proposed in the 1930s,
in fact these approaches even predate some
of the value function value estimate based
approaches we have talked about okay right.
So fine so we're all on board here so taking
this further now this looks like some kind
of ad hoc way of coming up with the policy
updates right, I mean it seems very natural
way of doing it why I get a reward I increase
the probability ok if I get a penalty I decrease
the probability seems like a very natural
way of doing it but is there a more systematic
way of thinking about learning the policy
directly right.
So there is a very well-studied and increasingly
a a direction which is receiving a lot of
attention called
policy gradient approaches, the book calls
these parameterized policy representations,
while the earlier one where you know value
function based methods they call this parameterized
policy approaches, so the basic idea here
is I am going to assume that my policies right,
so here I am giving you the policy as explicit
probability values right.
So I'm going to assume that my policy depends
on, the policy depends on some set of parameters,
so what do I mean by this, so my policy is
a probability distribution right I can specify
the probability distribution in many ways
for example I can specify the probability
distribution like we did earlier by a soft
max function right, so if I specify it by
a soft max function what is it that I need
to give you in order to define the policy
people remember soft max.
So e power something divided by summation
e power something right, so suppose I am saying
that I need to tell you what the soft max
function is corresponding to my current policy,
right so what is the information that I should
communicate to you, so all those exponents
that I am putting in there right for each
action I have something I put in the exponent
I will have to tell you that right, it need
not be values, just remember very much so
I am just talking about the soft max function
right however I derive the value that goes
into the exponent it can be a value function
it can be something else right.
I could have just arbitrarily pulled out some
numbers I could have said action 1 put a 3
in the exponent ok action 2 put a 15 in the
exponent action 3 put a 22 in the exponent
okay I just gave you those numbers arbitrarily
but this defines a policy, right however i
arrived at those numbers this defines a policy
right, so this is what I call as a parameterized
representation, so i have the set of parameters
ok that defined the policy for me so I the
parameters are somehow used to generate these
numbers for me right.
So this is essentially what we mean by parameters
so we have a set of parameters right they
could be anything they could be those values
that I plug into the exponents which sometimes
are called preferences okay, so that e power
thing there right, so I can just say I prefer
action a to action b right and then I can
have some way of converting that into actual
probabilities, right I would say my preference
for action a is 25, my preference for action
b is 13 right and from that I can convert
it into probabilities.
Because the value has a separate semantic
associated with it right the value is the
expected payoff that I am going to get on
pulling the arm when I say the preference
for the arm is 23 does not have need necessarily
have any semantics so 23 versus 15, so 23
is higher than 15 that is the only semantics
I have, right not necessarily that 23 means
that this is the payoff i am going to get
so this gives me a lot more flexibility in
how I change those values, right. it need
not necessarily come from the estimation of
the expectation okay right.
So it could be preferences it could be say
the weights of a neural network if you are
so inclined, right so this is something which
all of you should be thinking about how many
of you read this article about the go playing
agent? 1.2..3..4..5..6..7 not enough people
everybody go read the go playing agent about
alpha go...go go go to Google search for alpha
go, it is there in the Hindu for crying out
loud right, anyway.
So this is this machine learning agent which
they do not actually specify exactly what
is the machine learning algorithm that they
use it is a machine learning agent that learns
to play this game of Go which for a long long
long time was considered one of the hardest
games for computers to play because the number
of patterns that you could have are just huge,
right and rules are very simple but then it
turned out to be a very very hard game for
computers to play certainly not at human levels,
right but then Google deep mind has come up
as soon as say Google deep mind you should
know what algorithm that they use there right
at least what how they formulated the problem
right.
So they use reinforcement learning and a deep
neural network to train a go agent that actually
beat the European champion 5-0, I mean they
played a series of five matches and it beat
the champion on all five of them, right and
they are hoping to have a matchup with the
world champion go player, in March I do not
know.. they mentioned some dates March yeah
and maybe they still do not hope to beat the
world champion because apparently the world
champion player is at a much higher level
than, the all the other players out there
but still it so there is hope right.
So the point is RL plus neural networks seems
to be the hot thing nowadays right so everybody
wants to do that, right so this is not a esoteric
example if you are going to go out there and
do reinforcement learning this is probably
what you will end up doing right, so where
the parameters would be given by a weights
of a neural network, right and I'll give you
other examples as we go along right so even
this you can think of as a parameterized representation
right okay here is a question for you.
So what kind of a probability distribution
are we talking about here, binomial or Bernoulli
depending on whether it is repeated trials
or 1 trial right, so Bernoulli if I had multiple
actions it would have been a multinomial right
yeah so binomial multinomial so what is the
equivalent version of Bernoulli, actually
I mentioned this in ML class.. guys you know
who were there in the ML class should be able
to tell them.. I am not talking about the
conjugate priors boss.. I am saying for repeated
experiments, 2 outcome repeated experiments
is binomial single trial is Bernoulli, multiple
outcome repeated experience experiments is
multinomial, single experiment is categorical,
okay there is a distribution called the categorical
distribution which is essentially multiple
outcomes single single experiment probability
distributions okay but anyway.
So what are the parameters that describe binomial
distribution..
probability of 1 or something right.. so that
is essentially that so this is again one way
to think about this is this is also a parameterized
distribution, where I am specifying directly
the parameters of the multinomial or the binomial
in this case I just said a prime i could say
says all a prime not equal to a t and then
I have if I adjust this alpha then I basically
made it into a multinomial case ok
So this is also parameterized thing so I could
specify any kind of distribution like this
right so now what I am going to do is, just
like we did here i am going to modify the
policy parameters directly, right instead
of modified the value functions i will modify
the policy parameters directly what would
be a systematic way of doing this we can come
up with many things right so but I am talking
about a gradient based approach.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resources Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved